Medbh McGuckian papers, 1964-2006
Emory University
Medbh McGuckian papers, 1964-2006
McGuckian, Medbh, 1950-
Manuscript Collection No. 770
47 linear feet (92 boxes) and 30 oversized papers (OP)
Personal papers of Irish author Medbh McGuckian including correspondence, literary manuscripts, printed material, and audio-visual material.
Emory University Manuscript, Archives, and Rare Book Library
Source
Purchase, 1995 with subsequent additions.
Restrictions on Access
Special restrictions apply: Subseries 1.3 contains restricted correspondence of John Drexel and Marie and Seamus Heaney. Letters by Seamus and Marie Heaney are closed to researchers. Series 7, Unprocessed additions, unprocessed correspondence is closed to researchers.
Biographical Note
Medbh McGuckian was born in 1950 in Belfast, Northern Ireland. She received her Bachelor of Arts degree from Queen's University, Belfast, in 1972 and earned her Masters in Arts from the same institution two years later. McGuckian won the National Poetry Competition prize in 1979 for "The Flitting," and she published her first two collections of poetry, Single Ladies: Sixteen Poems and Portrait of Joanna, in 1980. Among her most recent collections are Had I a Thousand Lives, The Book of the Angel, and The Currach Requires No Harbours. In addition to being one of Ireland's foremost poets, McGuckian has also served as the editor of Fortnight Literary Magazine and has held numerous academic appointments, including serving as the Writer-in-Residence at her alma mater, Queen's University Belfast, and as a Creative Writing Lecturer at the Seamus Heaney Centre for Poetry there. McGuckian has also translated the work of several poets of different nationalities; notably, McGuckian and Eiléan Ní Chuilleanáin translated the poetry of Nuala Ní Dhomhnaill from Gaelic to English for The Water Horse (2000).
Scope and Content Note
The Medbh McGuckian papers comprises the literary and personal papers of the poet Medbh McGuckian from 1964-2006. The bulk of the collection consists of drafts of McGuckian's own writings, including drafts of poems from her first collection, Single Ladies, through The Currach Requires No Harbours. Also present are extensive files of personal and literary correspondence, which contain letters from Nuala Archer, Gerald Dawe, Theo Dorgan, Paul Durcan, Tess Gallagher, Seamus Heaney, Rita Ann Higgins, Jennifer Johnston, Michael Longley, Joan McBreen, Paul Muldoon, Nuala Ní Dhomhnaill, Dennis O'Driscoll, and others. The collection also includes writings by others (including student writing), subject files, collected printed material either by or about Medbh McGuckian, photographs, and sound recordings.
Arrangement Note
Organized into seven series: (1) Correspondence, (2) Writings by Medbh McGuckian, (3) Writings by others, (4) Personal files, (5) Printed material, (6) Audio-visual materials, and (7) Unprocessed additions.
Finding Aid Note
A selected index of prominent correspondents is available.
Related Materials in This Repository
Ciaran Carson papers, Michael Longley papers, Paul Muldoon papers, and Irish women poets oral history collection.
Selected Search Terms
Personal Names
Archer, Nuala, 1955-; Dawe, Gerald, 1952-; Dorgan, Theo.; Durcan, Paul, 1944-; Gallagher, Tess.; Heaney, Seamus, 1939-; Higgins, Rita Ann.; Johnston, Jennifer, 1930-; Longley, Michael, 1939-; McBreen, Joan, 1947-; Muldoon, Paul.; Ní Dhomhnaill, Nuala, 1952-; O'Driscoll, Dennis.
Topical Terms
Poets, Irish--20th century.; Irish poetry--20th century.; English poetry--Irish authors--20th century.; Women poets, Irish.
Geographic Names
Northern Ireland.
Form/Genre Terms
Manuscripts.; Photographs.; Poems.; Sound recordings.
Occupation
Woman poet.
Description of Series
- Correspondence, 1964-2006, Series 1; Box 1 - Box 15a
  Scope and Content Note
  The correspondence series in the Medbh McGuckian papers includes letters dating from 1964 to 2006, with the largest portion from the 1980s and 1990s. Literary correspondents include Nuala Archer, Gerald Dawe, Theo Dorgan, Paul Durcan, Tess Gallagher, Seamus Heaney, Rita Ann Higgins, Jennifer Johnston, Michael Longley, Joan McBreen, Paul Muldoon, Nuala Ní Dhomhnaill, and Dennis O'Driscoll. Subseries 1.2 contains correspondence between McGuckian and her publishers. Subseries 1.3 contains the restricted correspondence of John Drexel and Marie and Seamus Heaney. Additional correspondence is located in Subseries 4.2, Other subject files.
  Arrangement Note
  Organized into three subseries: (1.1) General correspondence, (1.2) Correspondence with publishers, and (1.3) Restricted correspondence.
  Finding Aid Note
  A selected index of prominent correspondents is available.
  Restrictions on Access
  Special restrictions apply: Subseries 1.3 contains restricted correspondence of John Drexel and Marie and Seamus Heaney. Letters by Seamus and Marie Heaney are closed to researchers.
  - General correspondence, 1964-2006, Subseries 1.1; Box 1 - Box 14a: Folder 3
    Arranged in chronological order.
    - 1964-1969 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 1960s, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 1970 January-July (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 1970 August-December, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 1971 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 1972 January-August (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 1972 September-December, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 1973 (Box 1a, Folder 1)
    - 1974 (Box 1a, Folder 2)
    - 1975-1976 (Box 1a, Folder 3)
    - 1977-1979 (Box 1a, Folder 4)
    - 1970s, undated (Box 1a, Folder 5)
    - 1980 (Box 1a, Folder 6)
    - 1981-April 1982 (Box 1a, Folder 7)
    - 1982 May-December (Box 1a, Folder 8)
    - 1983 January-March (Box 1a, Folder 9)
    - 1983 April-May (Box 1a, Folder 10)
    - 1983 June-December, undated (Box 1a, Folder 11)
    - 1984 January-March (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - 1984 April-July (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - 1984 August-December, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - 1985 January-December (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - 1986 January-March (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - 1986 April-May (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - 1986 June (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - 1986 July-August (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - 1986 September-October (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - 1986 November-December, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - 1987 January-February (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - 1987 March (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - 1987 April (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - 1987 May-June (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - 1987 July-August (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - 1987 September-October (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - 1987 November-December, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - 1988 January-February (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - 1988 March-April (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - 1988 May-June (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - 1988 July (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - 1988 August-September (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - 1988 October-November (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - 1988 December, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - 1989 January-February (Box 3a, Folder 1)
    - 1989 March-April (Box 3a, Folder 2)
    - 1989 May-June (Box 3a, Folder 3)
    - 1989 July-August (Box 3a, Folder 4)
    - 1989 September (Box 3a, Folder 5)
    - 1989 October (Box 3a, Folder 6)
    - 1989 November-December (Box 3a, Folder 7)
    - 1989, undated (Box 3a, Folder 8)
    - 1990 January-March (Box 3a, Folder 9)
    - 1990 April-May (Box 3a, Folder 10)
    - 1990 June-July (Box 3a, Folder 11)
    - 1990 August-September (Box 3a, Folder 12)
    - 1990 October-November (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - 1990 December, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - 1991 January (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - 1991 February (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - 1991 March-April (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - 1991 May (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - 1991 June-July (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - 1991 August-September (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - 1991 October-November (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - 1991 December, undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - 1992 January (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - 1992 February (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - 1992 March (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - 1992 April (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - 1992 May-June (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - 1992 July-August (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - 1992 September-October (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - 1992 November-December (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - 1992, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - 1993 January (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - 1993 February-April (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - 1993 May-June (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - 1993 July-August (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - 1993 September-October (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - 1993 November-December, undated (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - 1994 January (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - 1994 February (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - 1994 March (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - 1994 April (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - 1994 May (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - 1994 June (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - 1994 July (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - 1994 August (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - 1994 September (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - 1994 October (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - 1994 November (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - 1994 December, undated (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - 1995 January-February (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - 1995 March-April (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - 1995 May (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - 1995 June (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - 1995 July-August (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - 1995 September-October (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - 1995 November (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - 1995 December, undated (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - 1996 January-February (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - 1996 March-April (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - 1996 May (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - 1996 June (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - 1996 July-August (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - 1996 September (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - 1996 October (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - 1996 November-December, undated (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - 1997 January (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - 1997 February-March (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - 1997 April-May (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - 1997 June (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - 1997 July-August (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - 1997 September (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - 1997 October (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - 1997 November (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - 1997 December, undated (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - 1998 January (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - 1998 February (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - 1998 March-April (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - 1998 May-July (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - 1998 August-October (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - 1998 November-December, undated (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - 1999 January (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - 1999 February-March (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - 1999 April (Box 11a, Folder 1)
    - 1999 May (Box 11a, Folder 2)
    - 1999 June (Box 11a, Folder 3)
    - 1999 July-August (Box 11a, Folder 4)
    - 1999 September-October (Box 11a, Folder 5)
    - 1999 November-December, undated (Box 11a, Folder 6)
    - 2000 January-February (Box 11a, Folder 7)
    - 2000 March-April (Box 11b, Folder 1)
    - 2000 May-June (Box 11b, Folder 2)
    - 2000 July-October (Box 11b, Folder 3)
    - 2000 November-December, undated (Box 11b, Folder 4)
    - 2001 January-April (Box 11b, Folder 5)
    - 2001 May-August (Box 11b, Folder 6)
    - 2001 September-December, undated (Box 11c, Folder 1)
    - 2002 (Box 11c, Folder 2)
    - 2003 (Box 11c, Folder 3)
    - 2004 January-March (Box 11c, Folder 4)
    - 2004 April-September (Box 11c, Folder 5)
    - 2004 October-December, undated (Box 11c, Folder 6)
    - 2005 January-May (Box 11c, Folder 7)
    - 2005 June-December, undated (Box 11c, Folder 8)
    - 2006 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, undated, by indexed people, A-F (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, undated, by indexed people, G-Z (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, undated (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, undated (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, undated (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, undated (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, undated (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, undated (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, undated (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, undated (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, undated (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, undated (Box 13a, Folder 1)
    - Draft correspondence by McGuckian (Box 13a, Folder 2)
    - Faxes by McGuckian, 1996-2000, undated (Box 13a, Folder 3)
    - Birthday and anniversary cards, undated (Box 13a, Folder 4)
    - Christmas cards, undated (Box 13a, Folder 5)
    - Christmas cards, undated (Box 13a, Folder 6)
    - Christmas cards, undated (Box 13a, Folder 7)
    - Invitations, 1972-1993 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Invitations, 1994 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Invitations, 1995 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Invitations, 1996 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Invitations, 1997-1998 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Invitations, 1999 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Invitations, 2000 (Box 14a, Folder 1)
    - Invitations, 2001-2006 (Box 14a, Folder 2)
    - Invitations, undated (Box 14a, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence with publishers, 1978-2006, Subseries 1.2; Box 14a: Folder 4 - Box 15
    Arranged in alphabetical order.
    - The Blackstaff Press, 1978-1995 (Box 14a, Folder 4)
    - Bloodaxe Books, 1983-2000 (Box 14a, Folder 5)
    - Dedalus Press, undated (Box 14a, Folder 6)
    - Faber and Faber, 1981-1991 (Box 14a, Folder 7)
    - Farrar, Straus, and Giroux, Inc, 1987 (Box 14a, Folder 8)
    - The Gallery Press, 1990-1995 (Box 14a, Folder 9)
    - The Gallery Press, 1997-1999 (Box 14a, Folder 10)
    - The Gallery Press, 2000-2001 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - The Gallery Press, 2004-2006, undated (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Interim Press, 1979-1981 (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - Oxford University Press, 1981-1989 (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Oxford University Press, 1990-1994, undated (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - Penguin Books, 1983-1984 (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Salmon Press and New Poets, 1987 -1988 (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - University of California Press, 1989 (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - Wake Forest University Press, 1983-1999 (Box 15, Folder 9)
    - Wake Forest University Press, 2000-2004, undated (Box 15, Folder 10)
    - Other publishers (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - Restricted correspondence, Subseries 1.3; Box 15a
    Arranged in alphabetical order
    Special restrictions apply: Subseries 1.3 contains restricted correspondence. Letters by Seamus and Marie Heaney are closed to researchers.
    - Drexel, John (Box 15a, Folder 1)
    - Heaney, Marie (Box 15a, Folder 2)
    - Heaney, Seamus (Box 15a, Folder 3)
- Writings by Medbh McGuckian, Series 2; Boxes 16-30, OP 1-3
  The writings by Medbh McGuckian found in this series include collected and uncollected poetry, prose, translations by McGuckian, translations of McGuckian, and notebooks. The individual poems in Subseries 2.1 are filed alphabetically within each collected work; the collected works are arranged chronologically. Researchers should be aware that The Flower Master, Venus and the Rain, and On Ballycastle Beach were originally published by Oxford University Press and were reissued several years later by Gallery Press with minor changes to the content. Subseries 2.1 also includes three unpublished collections of poems; while some of the poems within these collections were eventually published, they were not published in these original groupings. Also included in Subseries 2.1 are several uncollected individual poems, arranged alphabetically. When multiple poems appear on a single manuscript page, cross references have been provided.
  Subseries 2.5 contains several of McGuckian's manuscript notebooks. These notebooks contain manuscript drafts of poems from Portrait of Joanna, The Flower Master and Other Poems, Venus and the Rain, Two Women, Two Shores, Marconi's Cottage, Captain Lavender, Shelmalier, Drawing Ballerinas, The Face of the Earth, and The Currach Requires No Harbours, as well as essays on literature, student compositions, and poetry by others in McGuckian's hand. Additional manuscripts of some of McGuckian's work may also be found in the diaries located in Subseries 4.1, Personal and Family Items.
  Organized into five subseries: (2.1) Poetry, (2.2) Prose, (2.3) Translations by McGuckian, (2.4) Translations of McGuckian, and (2.5) Notebooks.
  - Poetry, Subseries 2.1; Box 16 - Box 25: Folder 45; OP 1-3
    Arranged in chronological order by work, then in alphabetical order by poem title.
    - Portrait of Joanna (1980) [See also Subseries 2.5, Notebooks]
    - "The Badger," TS (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - "Chopping," TS (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - "Curtains," MS and TS (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - "Decisions," TS (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - "Fair Head," MS and TS (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - "The Flitting," MS and TS (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - "Ivy," TS (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - "The Music Centre," MS and TS (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - "Power Cut," MS and TS (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - "Problems," MS (Box 16, Folder 10)
    - "Ringleaders," MS and TS (Box 16, Folder 11)
    - "The Rose Pirate," MS and TS (Box 16, Folder 12)
    - "Saint Sophia," MS and TS (Box 16, Folder 13)
    - "Sand," TS (Box 16, Folder 14)
    - "The Seed-Picture," MS and TS (Box 16, Folder 15)
    - "Studies," TS [See also Subseries 2.1, Portrait of Joanna, "Fair Head" MS] (Box 16, Folder 16)
    - "Tulips," TS [See also Subseries 2.1, Portrait of Joanna, "Fair Head" MS] (Box 16, Folder 17)
    - "Tulips" (Box OP1)
    - The Flower Master and Other Poems (1982, 1993) [See also Subseries 2.5, Notebooks]
    - "Admiring the Furs," MS and TS [variant title: "Tupperware"] (Box 16, Folder 18)
    - "The Aphrodisiac," TS and proof (Box 16, Folder 19)
    - "Aunts," TS (Box 16, Folder 20)
    - "The Butterfly Farm," TS (Box 16, Folder 21)
    - "The Chain Sleeper," [See Subseries 2.1, Portrait of Joanna, "Problems" MS] (Box -, Folder -)
    - "Champagne," MS and TS (Box 16, Folder 22)
    - "Distance," MS and TS [variant title: "Interest"] (Box 16, Folder 23)
    - "The Dowry Murder," MS and TS (Box 16, Folder 24)
    - "Ducks and Drakes," MS and TS (Box 16, Folder 25)
    - "Faith," MS and TS (Box 16, Folder 26)
    - "The Flower Master," MS and TS (Box 16, Folder 27)
    - "The Flower Master" (Box OP2)
    - "Fossils," MS and TS (Box 16, Folder 28)
    - "The Gardener," TS [See also Subseries 2.1, The Flower Master and Other Poems, "The Flower Master" TS] (Box 16, Folder 29)
    - "Gateposts," TS (Box 16, Folder 30)
    - "Gentians," TS (Box 16, Folder 31)
    - "Gladiolus," TS [See also Subseries 2.1, The Flower Master and Other Poems, "The Flower Master TS] (Box 16, Folder 32)
    - "The Heiress," MS and TS (Box 16, Folder 33)
    - "The Hollywood Bed," TS (Box 16, Folder 34)
    - "The Katydid," MS and TS (Box 16, Folder 35)
    - "The Long Engagement," MS and TS [See also Subseries 2.1, The Flower Master and Other Poems, "Distance," MS and TS] (Box 16, Folder 36)
    - "Lucina," MS and TS [includes "January," "Losing," "Pica," "Lacewood," "Lamps," "The Sailor," "The Newborn," and "The Moon Pond"] [Subseries 2.1: also The Flower Master and Other Poems, "Aphrodisiac," "Champagne," "The Dowry Murder," and "Gentians"] (Box 16, Folder 37)
    - "Lychees," TS (Box 16, Folder 38)
    - "The Mast Year," TS (Box 16, Folder 39)
    - "My Mother," TS (Box 16, Folder 40)
    - "Next Day Hill," TS (Box 16, Folder 41)
    - "The Orchid House," TS [See also Subseries 2.1, The Flower Master and Other Poems, "Lucina" MS] (Box 16, Folder 42)
    - "The Perfect Mother," MS and TS (Box 16, Folder 43)
    - "The Problem Girl," MS and TS [variant title: "Stars"] (Box 16, Folder 44)
    - "The Retired Couple," TS (Box 16, Folder 45)
    - "The Singer," MS and TS (Box 16, Folder 46)
    - "Slips," MS and TS (Box 16, Folder 47)
    - "Smoke," TS (Box 16, Folder 48)
    - "The Sofa," TS (Box 16, Folder 49)
    - "The Soil-Map," MS and TS (Box 16, Folder 50)
    - "Spring," MS (Box 16, Folder 51)
    - "The Standing," TS (Box 16, Folder 52)
    - "The Sunbench," MS and TS (Box 16, Folder 53)
    - "The Sun-Trap," TS [See also Subseries 2.1, The Flower Master and Other Poems, "Fair Head" MS] (Box 16, Folder 54)
    - "Swing," MS and TS [variant title: "The Cage Cup"] (Box 16, Folder 55)
    - "That Year," TS (Box 16, Folder 56)
    - "The Theatre," MS and TS (Box 16, Folder 57)
    - "To My Grandmother," TS [See also Subseries 2.1, The Flower Master and Other Poems, "To My Grandmother," proof] (Box 16, Folder 58)
    - "The Truth Room," TS (Box 16, Folder 59)
    - "The Witchmark," TS (Box 16, Folder 60)
    - "Your House," TS [See also Subseries 2.1, The Flower Master and Other Poems, "Gentians," TS] (Box 16, Folder 61)
    - The Flower Master, book jacket (Box 16, Folder 62)
    - The Flower Master, galley proof (Oxford University Press) (Box OP3)
    - The Flower Master, bound galley proof (Oxford University Press) (Box 16, Folder 63)
    - List of poems not included in The Flower Master (Box 16, Folder 64)
    - Venus and The Rain (1984, 1994) [See also Subseries 2.5, Notebooks]
    - "Another Son," MS and TS (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - "The Apricot Ranch," MS and TS (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - "The Artemesia," MS and TS (Box 17, Folder 3)
    - "Aviary," MS and TS (Box 17, Folder 4)
    - "Catching Geese," MS and TS (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - "Confinement," MS and TS [variant title: "The Confinement"] (Box 17, Folder 6)
    - "Culprits," TS (Box 17, Folder 7)
    - "The Daisy Cutter," MS and TS (Box 17, Folder 8)
    - "A Day With Her," MS and TS (Box 17, Folder 9)
    - "The Difficult Age," MS and TS (Box 17, Folder 10)
    - "The Dovecote," MS and TS (Box 17, Folder 11)
    - "Epithalamium," MS and TS (Box 17, Folder 12)
    - "Felicia's Café," MS and TS (Box 17, Folder 13)
    - "For the Previous Owner," MS and TS (Box 17, Folder 14)
    - "Freeze-Up," MS and TS (Box 17, Folder 15)
    - "From the Dressing Room," TS [See also Subseries 2.1, The Flower Master and Other Poems, "The Aphrodisiac," proof] (Box 17, Folder 16)
    - "The Hard Summer," MS and TS [See also Subseries 2.1, The Flower Master and Other Poems, "The Aphrodisiac," proof] (Box 17, Folder 17)
    - "Harvest," MS and TS [variant title: "The Harvest"] (Box 17, Folder 18)
    - "Hotel," TS [variant title: "The Hotel"] [See also Subseries 2.1: Venus and The Rain, "Harvest," MS and TS] (Box 17, Folder 19)
    - "Isba Song," MS and TS (Box 17, Folder 20)
    - "Lime Trees in Winter, Retouched," MS and TS (Box 17, Folder 21)
    - "Mad River," MS and TS (Box 17, Folder 22)
    - "Miss Twelves," MS and TS (Box 17, Folder 23)
    - "Moonshots," MS (Box 17, Folder 24)
    - "Ode to a Poetess," MS and TS (Box 17, Folder 25)
    - "On Not Being Your Lover," MS and TS [See also Subseries 2.1, Venus and the Rain, "Epithalamium," TS] (Box 17, Folder 26)
    - "Pain Tells You What to Wear," MS and TS (Box 17, Folder 27)
    - "The Painter and the Poet," MS and TS [variant title: "Ruby Cottage (or an English Mile)"] (Box 17, Folder 28)
    - "Partly Dedicated to a House," TS (Box 17, Folder 29)
    - "Prie-Dieu," MS and TS (Box 17, Folder 30)
    - "The Princess of Parallelograms," MS and TS (Box 17, Folder 31)
    - "The Return of Helen," MS and TS (Box 17, Folder 32)
    - "The Rising Out," MS and TS (Box 17, Folder 33)
    - "Rowing," MS and TS (Box 17, Folder 34)
    - "Sabbath Park," MS and TS (Box 17, Folder 35)
    - "The Scattering," MS and TS (Box 17, Folder 36)
    - "The Sitting," MS and TS (Box 17, Folder 37)
    - "Sky House," MS and TS (Box 17, Folder 38)
    - "Something Like a Wind," MS and TS (Box 17, Folder 39)
    - "Star," MS and TS (Box 17, Folder 40)
    - "The Thursdayer," MS and TS [See also Subseries 2.1, Venus and the Rain, "The Princess of Parallelograms," MS] (Box 17, Folder 41)
    - "To the Nightingale," MS and TS (Box 17, Folder 42)
    - "Underground," MS and TS (Box 17, Folder 43)
    - "Vanessa's Bower," MS and TS (Box 17, Folder 44)
    - "Venus and the Rain," MS and TS [See also Subseries 2.1, Venus and the Rain, "Vanessa's Bower," TS] (Box 17, Folder 45)
    - "Venus and the Sun," MS and TS (Box 17, Folder 46)
    - "The Villain," TS (Box 17, Folder 47)
    - "Waters," MS and TS [See also Subseries 2.1, The Flower Master and Other Poems, "The Mast Year," TS] (Box 17, Folder 48)
    - Cover artwork [photocopy] (Box 17, Folder 49)
    - Proposed title page, MS (Box 17, Folder 50)
    - Title page and table of contents, TS (Box 17, Folder 51)
    - On Ballycastle Beach (1988, 1995)